Finding Aid for Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records, 1833-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.) records 1833-1981
Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
86783 Ba 2; BA Outsize
History, administrative and financial records, files of church organizations, publications, and papers of individual pastors; also record books (prior to 1875) of Frederick Schmid, formerly pastor of the Bethlehem Church, now Bethlehem United Church of Christ; and photographs.
16 linear feet
4 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was deposited with the library beginning in August 1982. Periodic additions are expected. Donor no. 6828.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
A microfilm copy of select portions of the records is available including
Ladies Aid Society
History of the Ladies Aid Society
Minutes
1877-1929 (in German)
1920-1930 (in English)
Record Books (includes baptisms, confirmation, marriage and death records)
1975-1947
Congregational records: Francis Schmid
Baptismal Book, 1833-1875
Family Register, beginning 1833
Marriage Records, 1833-1871
The early history of the Zion Lutheran Church of Ann Arbor parallels the career of Reverend Frederick Schmid. Reverend Schmid came to Ann Arbor from Germany and established the Zion Church in Scio Township in 1833 and the Bethlehem Church in Ann Arbor in 1849. He served as pastor of the Bethlehem Church until his retirement in 1871 and was succeeded by Reverend Herman Reuter. The question of a new location for the Bethlehem Church split the congregation in 1875. A number of the members, including Reverend Schmid, withdrew from the Bethlehem Church and organized the Zion Lutheran Church.
The first service of the Zion Lutheran Church, July 11, 1875, was held at the old Congregational Church on Fifth and Washington Avenues. The leaders of this new church bought the Congregational Church and named the Reverend Herman Frederick Belser (1875-1890) to serve as the congregation's first pastor. Reverend Belser served as pastor until his retirement in 1890. He was succeeded by Reverend Max Hein. During Reverend Hein's ministry (1890-1895) the church was torn down and a new building was erected on the same location. The dedication service was December 9, 1894.
In 1896 Reverend A. L. Nicklas accepted the position of pastor at Zion Lutheran. During Reverend Nicklas' 21 years at Zion Lutheran (1896-1917) the church's activities and congregation grew. The church was also remodeled to accommodate the growing congregation. Reverend Nicklas left the church in 1917 and was replaced by Reverend E. C. Stellhorn. Reverend Stellhorn's ministry (1917-1947) witnessed a number of changes in the church. These included the closing of the parochial "German" school, having English replace German as the predominant language of the church, and establishing a daily vacation Bible school and the Lutheran Students Association for University of Michigan students.
Although Reverend Stellhorn retired in 1947, he was active in church affairs and had the title of Pastor Emeritus. Succeeding Reverend Stellhorn was Reverend Howard F. Yeager (1947-1952). Plans for expansion were carried forward during Reverend Yeager's ministry and in 1948 the decision was made to build a new church on West Liberty Road. Reverend Yeager coordinated the plans until his death in 1952 at the age of 38. His successor, Reverend Ralph B. Piper (1953-1973), supervised the move to the new church which was completed in 1958. The size of the clerical staff under Reverend Piper grew with new positions created for parish education, music, and other pastoral duties. The disbursement of pastoral responsibilities resulted in a team ministry which grew specifically from a congregational self-study. Reverend Piper resigned in 1973 and was succeeded by Reverend Robert Huff. Reverend Huff was installed as the team ministry leader.
The records of Zion Lutheran Church of Ann Arbor span the years 1875-1981. Those records in the collection which date before 1875 were kept by the Rev. Frederick Schmid probably when he was minister of the Bethlehem Church. These record books (in box 12) include two volumes of baptismal records, a family register, and a record book of marriages performed. These four volumes date from 1833 to approximately 1875 when Zion was established. The volumes are in German.
Except for these volumes, the records in the collection are of Zion Lutheran Church. Included are historical materials, administrative and financial records, records of church organizations, church bulletins and newsletters, membership records, and sermons and collected materials of the church's pastors. The earlier records of the church are usually in German.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Bethlehem Evangelical Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); German Americans--Michigan.; Lutheran Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Evangelical Synod of North America--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.; Women--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; German Americans--Michigan.; Lutheran Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Singing.; Zion Lutheran Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Schmid, Friedrich, 1807-1883
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- History
  The historical files include anniversary histories and materials collected in the preparation of these histories.
  - 1875-1915 (Box 1)
  - World War I (Box 1)
  - 1925, 1950 Anniversaries (Box 1)
  - 1957 Cornerstone (Box 1)
  - 1975 Centennial (Box 1)
  - Centennial History (unpublished), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Administrative and Financial Records
  The administrative and financial files include (in part) annual reports, constitutions, congregational minutes, and minutes of the vestry church council.
  - Financial Records
    - 1800s undated (Box 1)
    - 1908-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1931-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1953-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1960-1962 (Box 1)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1981 (Box 2)
  - Constitutions (Box 2)
  - Constitution Revisions 1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Membership Committee 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Minutes
    - Congregational Minutes
      - 1875-1925 (including early membership list), 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1925-1953 (Box 2)
      - 1954-1962 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1973 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Committees (Box 2)
    - Monitoring Committee Minutes
      - 1954-1957 (Box 2)
      - 1957-1959 (Box 2)
    - Music Committee Minutes 1958-1967 (Box 2)
    - Vestry-Church Council Minutes
      - 1875-1889 (Box 3)
      - 1889-1909 (Box 3)
      - 1916-1919 (Box 3)
      - 1919-1930, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      - 1930-1941, 1 volumes (Box 3)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 3)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 3)
      - 1948-1953 (Box 3)
      - 1953-1958 (Box 3)
      - 1958-1962 (Box 3)
      - 1962-1965 (Box 3)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 3)
      - 1969-1972 (Box 3)
  - Mission Treasury 1875-1919 (Box 4)
- Church Organizations
  Under church organizations are filed records of each of the different groups which operated within the church: youth, women's organizations, and seniors groups.
  - Brotherhood Records
    - Board and General Meetings
      - 1927-1929 (Box 4)
      - 1938-1942 (Box 4)
      - 1960-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 4)
    - Cashbook 1918-1937 (Box 4)
    - Christian Service Committee 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Congregational Service Committee 1961-1966 (Box 4)
    - Constitution and By-Laws 1967 et. al. (Box 4)
    - Membership (Box 4)
    - Men of the Church (Box 4)
    - Minutes
      - 1917-1922, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1922-1927, 1 volumes (Box 4)
      - 1944-1947 (Box 4)
      - 1952-1957 (Box 4)
      - 1958-1960 (Box 4)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 5)
      - 1963 (Box 5)
      - 1964 (Box 5)
      - 1965 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Monthly News 1963 (Box 5)
    - Monthly Program Committee 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Work Council Meeting 1961-1963 (Box 5)
  - Boy Scouts (Box 5)
  - Dorcas Society
    - Financial Records 1949-1958 (Box 5)
    - Minutes 1951-1958 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Emma's Club 1934-1969 (Box 5)
  - Ladies Aid Society
    - Dues Records
      - 1896-1906 (Box 6)
      - 1906-1908 (Box 6)
      - 1908-1909 (Box 6)
      - 1910-1911 (Box 6)
      - 1912-1913 (Box 6)
      - 1914-1915 (Box 6)
      - 1916-1917 (Box 6)
      - 1927-1931 (Box 6)
    - Financial Records
      - 1926-1936 (Box 6)
      - 1950-1958 (Box 6)
    - History of the Ladies Aid Society (Box 6)
      (microfilm copy available)
    - Membership (Box 6)
    - Minutes (In German)
      - 1897-1899 (Box 6)
      - 1900-1906 (Box 6)
      - 1907-1912 (Box 6)
      - 1913-1918 (Box 6)
      - 1918-1925 (Box 6)
    - Minutes (In English)
      (microfilm copy available of these records from 1920 to 1930)
      - 1920-1923 (Box 6)
      - 1923-1927 (Box 6)
      - 1927-1929 (Box 6)
      - 1929-1933 (Box 7)
      - 1933-1934 (Box 7)
      - 1935-1937 (Box 7)
      - 1937-1939 (Box 7)
      - 1939-1942 (Box 7)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 7)
      - 1945-1946 (Box 7)
      - 1947-1951 (Box 7)
      - 1951-1956 (Box 7)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 7)
    - Memorials (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Scrapbook (Volume 1)
  - Luther Student Center (Box 7)
  - Luther League
    - 1950-1951 (Box 7)
    - 1967-1969 (Box 7)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 7)
  - Music (Box 7)
  - Parish Education
    - Minutes 1948-1963, 3 volumes; 1 folders (Box 8)
    - Reports, correspondence, and notes (Box 8)
  - Reports (Box 8)
  - Retirement Center (Box 8)
  - Sons of Zion (Box 8)
  - Sunday School
    - Ledgers 1875-1893, 1932-1951, 2 volumes (Box 8)
    - Minutes 1892-1908, 1922-1940, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Vicars (Box 8)
  - Women's Missionary Federation (Box 8)
  - Youth Society-German October 1896-October 1911, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Zion Lutheran Church Women-Minutes
    - 1958-1959 (Box 8)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 8)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 8)
    - 1964-1965 (Box 8)
    - 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - Zion Senior Young People's Society (Box 8)
- Church Publications
  The collection includes some church publications, such as a series of church bulletins, and the church newsletter The Tower.
  - Bulletins
    - 1944-1964 (Box 9)
    - 1965-1973 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - The Tower (Box 11)
- Congregational Records-Zion Lutheran Church
  This series consists of records of baptisms and marriages, confirmations, and notices of death. There is also some other materials relating to the church's membership.
  - Record books
    (including baptisms, confirmations, marriages and death records)
    - 1875-1894, 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - 1894-1924, 1 oversize volumes (Volume 2)
    - 1925-1947, 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - 1940s-1959 (Box 12)
    - 1950s-1960s (Box 12)
  - Confirmations
    - 1897-1953, 1 volumes (Box 12)
    - 1968-1974 (Box 12)
    - Reunions, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Scrapbook 1917-1942 (Box 12)
  - Baptismal record book 1896-1897, 1 volumes (Box 13)
  - Communicant record book 1911-1918 (Volume 3)
  - Death notices
    - 1960-1962 (Box 13)
    - 1963-1965 undated (Box 13)
  - Correspondence and Special Programs, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
- Congregational Records: Frederick Schmid
  This series consists of baptismal and other records maintained by Frederick Schmid.
  (microfilm copy available of these records)
  - Baptismal book 1833-1844, 1 volumes (Box 13)
  - Baptismal book 1845-1875, 1 volumes (Box 13)
  - Family register, beginning 1833, 1 volumes (Box 13)
  - Marriage book 1833-1871, 1 volumes (Box 13)
- Pastors' Files
  Pastors' files consist of sermons and obituary messages of E. C. Stellhorn, as well as personal and collected information on many of the church's other pastors.
  - Akre, Charles H. (Box 14)
  - Belser, Herman F. (Box 14)
  - Bracklein, David F. (Box 14)
  - Freytag, Ralph C. (Box 14)
  - Harms, Fred (Box 14)
  - Holtfreter, Fred (Box 14)
  - Huff, Robert (Box 14)
  - Kotchenruther, Wilson (Box 14)
  - Linter, David F. (Box 14)
  - Nicklas, Alexander L. (Box 14)
  - Piper, Ralph B. (Box 14)
  - Schmid, Frederick (Box 14)
  - Shaffer, Floyd (Box 14)
  - Stellhorn, E.C. (Box 14)
  - Yeager, Howard F. (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook 1936-1969 concerning church pastors (Volume 4)
- Sermons
  - Stellhorn, E. C., 2 boxes (Box 14)
  - Stellhorn, E. C., 2 boxes (Box 15)
  - Chronological series 1959-1965, 8 folders (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous
  - 1994, 1996 accessions (scattered later material) (Box 15)
- Photographs
  The photos are of church buildings, choirs, confirmation classes and reunions, events, organizations, pastors, and schools.
  - Buildings
    - First church (before 1894) (Box 16)
    - Second church 1894-1958
      - Exterior (Box 16)
      - Interior (Box 16)
    - Third church (1956- )
      - Site (Box 16)
      - Groundbreaking (Box 16)
      - Construction (Box 16)
      - Exterior (Box 16)
      - Interior (Box 16)
    - Parish Hall (Box 16)
    - Parsonages (Box 16)
  - Choirs
    - 1912-1950 (Box 16)
    - 1951-1960 (Box 16)
    - 1961-1970 (Box 16)
    - 1971-1980 (Box 16)
  - Confirmation classes and reunions
    - 1888-1910 (Box 16)
    - 1911-1930 (Box 16)
    - 1931-1980s (Box 16)
  - Events
    - 75th Anniversary Parish Night 1950 (Box 16)
    - Mortgage Burning 1971 (Box 16)
    - Installation of Rev. Huff 1973 (Box 16)
    - Stewardship Dinner 1974 (Box 16)
    - Centennial 1975 (Box 16)
    - Outdoor worship (Box 16)
    - Picnics and festivals (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified (Box 16)
  - Organizations
    - Altar Guild (Box 16)
    - Brotherhood Constitution (Box 16)
    - Ladies Aid Society (Box 16)
    - Luther League (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified
      - Women (Box 16)
      - Youth (Box 16)
  - Pastors
    - Schmid, Belser, Hein, Nicklas (Box 16)
    - Stellhorn (Box 16)
    - Piper (Box 16)
    - Huff and others (Box 16)
  - Schools
    - Parish School (Box 16)
    - Summer School (Box 16)
    - Summer Sunday School (Box 16)
    - Sunday School (Box 16)
    - Vacation Bible School (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16)